[Music]
welcome everyone i also feel really
excited about this conversation
aisha we we met probably about a month
ago
the reason we're having this
conversation now is because after the
interview i did with you
i went into my bag and i pulled out i've
forgotten it was in there but i pulled
out diane's book
the zen of you and me and it it felt so
appropriate for what we've just been
talking about that i thought
i'm gonna i thought this this is meant
for you so so i gave it to you
yes there it is and
it felt really appropriate and i gave it
to you and
then you were you messaged me you i
think you were reading on the bus and
you said oh i'm really enjoying the book
and i just thought there was a really
natural segue and a really
natural connection that was there with
diane who
i've known diane now for probably
eight months maybe almost a year we we
had the the privilege the privilege of
hanging out with diane for a bit in
california
and also is one of the most grounded
embodied empathetic compassionate uh
people that i that i've spent time with
and you both have that quality and it
just
felt like a very natural um
it felt like a very natural meeting that
that you obviously were both up
for and both keen to make happen well
first of all i just want to
thank everybody for being on the call
and i'm really honored
to meet you aisha today it's a such a
pleasure
so great to listen to your interview
with david and to read about you online
and to see what you've been
up to and how you're just so beautifully
expressing yourself
and your your convictions and your
clarity
i've i'm deeply moved by it and david
just a big shout out to you
i mean yeah i'm assuming you're both
brits is that
the case so you know apparently we're
we're friends
you know from way back close to each
other in southampton we actually come
from the same city
oh is that right is that right and
almost no one comes from there so that's
really interesting oh really that is
interesting yeah
when i i first spoke with david um and
one thing that attracted me to rebel
wisdom in general
was the fact that it was talking about
cultural issues and things going on of
the moment but it was also
looking at it from frameworks that were
maybe slightly more
mystical or spiritual and these are
things that
aren't there isn't much space for
necessarily i don't see
in the in the mainstream public
discourse
and the way that i've come to this
conversation has never been political
um i've come to this conversation um
maybe through something that people
could consider close to
yeah something of a of a more spiritual
inclination
i recognize that you know there is so
much more to
us to each other um
then we're often led to believe or we
often allow ourselves to see
um and i recognize that there are
certain ways of being
that can really
stop us from recognizing our commonality
and when i saw things deepening
in in that sense you know stopping this
type of recognition that we have
that's what got me very curious about
this cultural shift
and this moment it wasn't for me or left
or right thing
it just seemed that you know
that there could be another way to look
at some of these
really contentious issues from a lens
that wasn't
solely political um and so when i was
speaking uh to david i was saying you
know like
i'm very interested in maybe trying to
come across someone who
who is maybe thinking about these things
from from another maybe more humanistic
angle and then there you are in his bag
and i i did read the book and and it was
um
it was really uh you know because i had
no expectations you know when he
gave it to me i mean i'm at the point at
the moment i get books given to me often
um and you know you don't always you
kind of just half take it you don't
really know what to expect you know and
you're just
kind of grateful and you're not sure if
you're going to read it
but you take it anyway um
but i did i was on the bus and and i
have been
i don't know just thinking a lot
recently
uh as often and and especially with
a new sort of increased platform i guess
i'm very much thinking about
how how best to serve
you know and i just thought that maybe
your book would have something in it and
it very much did
um and then i i did some more research
and you know i see you talking about
compassionate conversations
and maybe one of the things that i'm
trying to learn how to do
is how do we make people with
opposing views see that the other side
isn't evil
you know but maybe just how do we show
people that others who they disagree
with just have different understandings
of what is good
rather than i'm trying to deliberately
subjugate
and oppress you of course that happens
intentionally in some areas but i
personally don't believe
that's what most people set out to do
and so i'm just wondering
you know like how do you know what are
some of the tools that you think for
having more compassionate conversations
one of the things that comes up a lot in
conversation these days
you know i i think in relationship to
wolf culture and to
you know basically the the effort to try
to genuinely
create equality which is the the upside
in my experience of what's happening in
terms of
um this kind of you you said something i
thought was interesting you talked about
the difference between being woke
as though it's a done deal an awakening
which is an ongoing process so whatever
this
wave of awakening is that's trying to
happen you know one of the things that
we're asked to do a lot
and i think it's it's good for all of us
is just simply learn how to listen
learn how to listen to somebody else's
experience that is different from our
own
that maybe they've drawn different
conclusions and different beliefs based
on that
and to be able to do it in such a way
where we distinguish what we're hearing
[Music]
from agreement we may agree we may not
we may have a different set as you were
saying with david that
really different set of life experiences
but our capacity to receive
and hear someone else's experience that
that language of you know can i
understand i don't quite know what that
means can i hear and can i take in
what someone else is telling me
absolutely i can't without a doubt so
that quality that ability to really
listen and receive and not allow our own
reference points our own desires our own
needs to get in the way
i think is a fundamental skill that we
all need to have
so even just the way that you're
listening to me right now i can feel the
quality
of your receptivity you're actually
taking in what i'm saying
you know so i think that's super
fundamental because it's easy to listen
when i hear something i agree with
it's easy to listen when i hear
something that i'm at least open to but
it gets really difficult to listen
when i hear something that i don't agree
with and even harder to listen when i
myself feel criticized
or challenged or called out or whatever
you know that's one of the real skill
sets that we need to develop
as an inability to realize that we can
listen in spite of being stressed
you know that's something we can do so i
would start there with just
that basic skill and so
why do you think that you know i i think
you're right i think listening
really is key of course and it sounds
simple but
i mean i don't think many of us do it
very well we don't
we think we do but we actually don't
especially when we're stressed
exactly but i often think that it's
it's probably the things that we
disagree with that we probably need to
pay closer attention to
yeah you know or probably that we need
to listen to more of i think and
and maybe it's worked in my favor but
i've always just been
very naturally interested in ideas that
i disagree with
um because i've always been keen to know
well how does someone get to that you
know like because i guess if you truly
do maybe think an idea is harmful you
know
rather than condemning that idea off the
bat i mean which you
can do but if you want to maybe stop the
flow of those ideas then you have to be
able to understand
like you know what drives people or
draws people into these types of things
um so yeah i've always i i really think
that
that type of thing um yeah listening to
or becoming more curious about
what we dislike i think is is quite key
yeah well i i think it's something that
you i've observed both you and david do
well and it might be fun at some point
during the conversation
maybe we can find a way to disagree with
each other so we can model that i mean i
think one of the
one of the things that we tend not to
see very much online is we don't see
healthy disa well maybe we do do you
guys feel like you see people
disagree and challenge each other online
you're right because when i was
listening to you today
i remember you said something somewhere
and i think actually this might have
been around the metoo movement you were
speaking to someone about that
and i think somewhere you said something
like you like to
um you like to encourage disagreement
sometimes
absolutely to work with that and i think
that's interesting because i
would say you're right when it comes to
um
podcasts and alternative media i guess
often we're speaking to people who who
agree with us
yeah exactly yeah we don't often have
that space so i wouldn't i would say on
twitter i often find
that the way that i use twitter and i've
been very grateful because i see that it
doesn't happen with many
people but sometimes people disagree
with me and they're
it's the most it's the most beautiful
disagreements i've ever heard you know
like yeah you're just kind of more than
sort of
angry or aggressive they're just kind of
like oh you haven't considered this
do you remember this yeah and i'm just
like oh well thank you
um i couldn't consider that i will next
time yeah
so sometimes on twitter it happens uh
but generally speaking no i don't see it
very often
so that's something i think we can
actually start to model and we've been
talking with david a little bit about
what would it be like to actually start
to have conversations
with people of really different world
views and see what we can learn about
doing it online
so the the curiosity that you're that is
such a driver of
how you relate to the world you know
fundamentally
one has to have one has to be a good
questioner now how do you ask good
questions how do you know as you said
you like to actually you gravitate
towards
opinions that aren't your own because
you're interested in how people arrived
at them so that very process of inquiry
that process of questioning of being
curious
i think is another one and again i will
say that
you know the channel has done a great
job with working with polyvagal
theory and working with embodiment and
working with somatic responses
but lots of times what keeps us from
either listening or inquiring in a real
way is
literally just the responsive threat in
the nervous system
for you to be able to hear something you
disagree with and be
curious is actually counter-intuitive
usually we move away from the thing
right it's like almost like amoeba you
know there's a stimulus and if it's
something that we don't like we just
simply move away
and so to turn and inquire into that is
counter-intuitive
you know so that that's that's an
amazing thing to be able to do in my
mind
well thank you and again it's from life
experiences that i've had so far you
know
you watched the interview with david and
i you know i
i spoke about you know my brother's
passing and wanting to understand
what happened you know essentially what
could drive a young man to take someone
else's life and things like that
and i think once you're dealing with
you know tragic things like that i guess
everything else if i'm honest it doesn't
really
it doesn't feel as threatening in
comparison
uh you know so as much as that was a
really tragic situation like i'm
i'm grateful for the sort of
how can i put it i'm grateful for the
tolerance it's given me
in in a certain way um
yeah i i guess so um
it's also going to say to you um
and also what i found really interesting
in the book and which is something that
i never knew about before and i guess i
mentioned it to david in the beginning
is you know you talk about these
different
stages of being maybe is maybe what i
can call it and i remember
the ethnocentric stage the world-centric
stage and things like this
um do we
how do we because maybe it's not
possible to um
help people sort of move through these
stages i'm starting to believe that
it's something people can only do on
their own but so
for let's say like people like myself
who are quite
critical you know or concerned about the
excesses
of the woke movement if you like
um i've been trying to tell myself for
some time now you know
when i'm trying to not get too
frustrated and i'm trying to and also
remember that i've been in that place
in many ways you know how do we try to
how can we remind people because i think
there's a danger in
in becoming so anti the thing that you
don't like that you are also now
that thing and so how do we sort of
because what i don't see i think enough
of sometimes is
you know i don't often see people trying
to understand
their world view enough because what i
see there and i think it's overlooked a
lot is
a lot of pain you know anger yeah
anger is a anger is a more sort of
socially acceptable presentation of pain
you know but i think it's pain and hurt
that's really there
um and which is why i try not to be
demeaning
of them i may be critical but not
i hear that yeah i hear that um
so there are kind of three different
things going on for me and what you
what you're saying right now so the
first one is just back to that original
question
that you posed at the beginning around
state stages structure stages of
development
and what does that have to do with
everything so a little something on that
and then the other two things i heard
you say
is that people that how humans develop
and grow is a bit of a mystery you're
starting to think people can't be
coerced they actually it has to be
something
almost that you elect into and i think
you're right about that
and then the question of how is pain
and maybe we can use the word trauma
because that's you know people are
working with trauma these days
how can trauma be related with
in a way that we become liberated and
free to love rather than
now oriented around how traumatized we
are because that's the other danger of
trauma right is that then
it becomes the identity so you know how
do we actually work with that so just in
terms of state stages
i found stages of development really
helpful to me in my mediation work
and as i said in my book i went from i
just naturally started using elizabeth
kubler ross's stages of grief because i
was doing work at the time
a lot of conversations related to race i
was working in the judiciary and
we had a racial and ethnic fairness task
force and this was 20 years ago i can't
believe how long it's been
and i just saw such a range of
availability
and the way people showed up in the
conversation
from denial all the way to absolute flex
flexible warm-hearted freedom
availability creativity that i was just
i couldn't help but start to create
categories
you know of people right regardless of
race or ethnicity people who were
you know in denial that there were any
issues people who were angry and
advocating at the top of their lungs
fair enough people who'd kind of found a
niche that worked for them
bargaining people who were just didn't
want to relate and were
sad and then these as i said before just
these people who were immensely free and
i got very curious that's when i was
introduced to ken's work
so one of the things that i think is
important is how identity
is held in the body mind has a lot to do
with
what we're able to experience and what
we're able to convey and communicate
with so when i hear you talk
what i hear you say is i can pick up an
identity
but i am very in touch with that in
myself that's beyond identity
i'm not limited to the fact that i'm
black i'm not limited to the fact that
i'm a woman i'm not limited to
my sexual identity or my gender identity
it's actually
fluid and sometimes people do relate to
that
as a privilege there's a privilege to be
free of identity and
and you know there may be some truth in
that but what i say in
compassionate conversations that i think
is important is it's a privilege i want
everyone to be able to experience
it's a privilege we want to share to be
free of identity
and i think we can and sorry that's a
really i'm glad you brought that up and
you know it was just a few weeks ago
that i've been thinking about identity
and i think
in my own personal journey i don't know
how much i promote it
maybe subtly i'm sure it can't help but
creep into my ideas
um but i'm very interested in this idea
of transcending identity
and it's very interesting that you point
out from speaking to me
that you know or you can clearly feel
that
i'm not someone who i try not to be
someone bound by my race
you know gender sexuality or anything
like that
you said it those are the least
interesting parts of yourself i thought
that was
that was a really interesting thing to
say and it made me think like
maybe those are the least interesting
parts of myself i haven't thought about
it so i feel
i love that you said that well thank you
well i'd like to i'd like to think so
i'd like to think that those
and and i think maybe one of the reasons
why i take
a lot of the time that we're living in
now to heart is that many people are
intent on telling me that actually the
most interesting thing about
is being black um and i think i find
that very difficult
and i think because if we're telling
people the most interesting things about
them are their identity
um then they will never know what can be
beyond that and there is something about
identity that i do find quite limiting
um and i'm saying it probably just on
twitter the other day that i think
the fixation with our identities can
limit our identities yeah you know
so let's say i'm a black you know woman
and so maybe that means that i can only
listen to or read other black women and
anything that isn't that i'm going to be
naturally hostile about or
considered to be a threat you know i'm
just limiting my own world view
um or you know my ability limiting my
my own capacity to connect with people
and so
but the problem is like identity right
now
is is so um
big you know it's so important for
people and
you know i i'm but i feel a real freedom
you know and i can't necessarily i'm not
saying my life is perfect and that you
can
i don't know buy your way into a ferrari
but what i am saying is that like
i i feel a sense of freedom you know i
feel a great sense of freedom in being
able to use my my short time here
and i'm very hyper aware of that to um
that's something you and i have in
common
interesting yes i did read that in your
book i remember i
i smiled to myself and i felt comforted
because i think you were talking about
your sister
and you were talking about you know the
differences between you and your sister
and you were the type of child who was
always
contemplating the meaning of life right
yeah yeah
that was definitely me um my sister was
crushing it
you know yeah right right and so yeah no
that's completely completely new
she still is oh no i i care
um so yeah you know how how do you think
we kind of go about you know because i
guess
in order to transcend identity people
want to
want to know what's left you know it's
not my identity if it's not my blackness
or my manhood or
you know my femininity then then what is
for me and so
can i ask you a question about that
because one of the things that i found
really interesting is when you talked
about your the i i loved that
and i'm i'm thinking about those of you
who are listening right now you know
like
one of the things that we do know in
developmental theory is that lots of
times there's a crisis
when people will shift identity or shift
stages or be able to take on more world
views or or more perspectives
something like like they come to an
existential crisis
or a loss but when you describe that
lying on the bed and seeing a slideshow
of all your most fundamental questions
that were extremely raw
and very intimate and in a certain way
what i heard you say is
you they couldn't be avoided and that
the answers were so
in in some ways like um what would
what would the word be you said raw that
you were so
intimate with yourself and there was
sort of no getting out of it
in a way and and to me i'm curious
what gave you access to this part of
yourself
that isn't limited by your respective
identities
and was it related to that crisis how
did you
how how did you get in touch with this
part of yourself and how do you
recognize it
as being beyond identity
um is it is that a good is that
it is a question such a good question i
probably may not have thought about it
so i so like i said for me
it was um you know the catalyst was you
know a close death in the family
um and it was you know the first time
i'd ever experienced something like that
and immediately i could tell by the way
that people responded in my family
that they didn't actually have much
belief you know i
they did have beliefs my family are
muslims um
however you know this sounds weird to
say and i don't mean any disrespect to
them or and of course definitely not to
the faith
but what it seemed as though is that
they were clinging on to religion
almost kind of as an insurance policy as
a kind of like you know just in case you
know i'm gonna hold on to this but
i could see they couldn't always lean on
it um
for for warmth and and and sort of
protection when they most needed it
and so that made me think well what is
that thing you know because people are
gonna i'm gonna keep losing people
you know people even closer potentially
so what am i gonna do
um and i guess that kick started this um
this search for something and at first
that was for maybe a tribe maybe a
community
maybe a truth or maybe something
akin to that and
i don't know i think that
i think when i realized how
when i realized that you know so from
this sort of awakening that i had
i realized how much of myself i'd
cut myself off from because it didn't
fit the narrative
of maybe what a black girl does what a
woman does what a woman is supposed to
think
what a black person on the left is
supposed to think or maybe
um just all of these things became very
very suffocating they were very
suffocating all of a sudden
um and i recognized i'd always had the
ability to connect with anyone of any
race gender you know background social
class
um you know it's very
hard for me to explain um but it's sorry
it's really good to think about and i'm
really trying to give like um
a real answer but i just i just looked
around me and i saw that
it seemed to me that people cling to
identity
because they were scared of this other
thing this other thing
that isn't always so pretty sometimes
it's a bit dark sometimes a
bit messy and it definitely isn't the
image of
yourself that you like to portray
everywhere
but once i realize that that thing
doesn't make you bad
yes yeah yeah yeah once i realized that
acknowledging these um
undesirable aspects of yourself that do
not make you bad once i took good and
bad
out of my vocabulary almost at least in
the way that i think
um i think that made it very easy
to explore anything that's what you're
saying is
so important right now because i think
it's the piece that when people do
diversity work
that they don't do well at all which is
if we're gonna
if we're gonna substantiate a difference
we're gonna substantiate a difference
based on our race based on our gender
based on whatever religion whatever it
is
we have to unpack how quickly we assign
good and bad to those differences
because it's there immediately so if we
don't help people
unpack and let go of those value
judgments
we're we're just creating difference and
binding people to these up and down
relationships so what i hear you saying
is that that there was some way in which
your encounter with
your life yourself including
the things that you were trying to do
the ways you were trying to be but also
those things
maybe we would call those things shadow
that the part of ourselves
that we feel like we can't show to the
world because they're too shameful
and that when you when you un
coupled those ex that part of who you
are from this value judgment of good and
bad
that was where freedom was for you
that's incredible yeah no
and you know so now i tried i tried to
think of
good and bad i only tried to think of
things in terms of
um constructive and and destructive yeah
so
i try not to you know so and and that
for me and so that only tells me if
something
is productive or construct you know
productive or useful or not
but it isn't about something being uh
morally you know incorrect and things
like that
and so yeah it just yeah i really think
it you know
it truly does give us a sense of freedom
within ourselves
but also when i acknowledged some of the
things that make me ashamed
of myself you know and some of the
things that were living in me
and recognizing to what extent that they
were unspeakable some of these things
and then recognizing that everybody
because i'm not that unique
you know we're all living with our own
versions of these things
you know and you know it really started
you know and i really felt for everyone
i really felt for everyone you know some
of yeah
somehow i really feel for everyone too
yeah no for sure
like some of the most all of the things
that make us maybe the most
human are some of the hardest things to
share totally and like you said that one
of the
other things you and i have in common is
my kind of existential confrontation
also came in the wake of death you know
where i lost these friends
i lost seven friends in like six months
and uh four in a plane and one committed
suicide anyway
that six month period was just this
really really deep
and i didn't have a lot of guidance it
doesn't sound like you had guidance
particularly like this was just an
encounter you had kind of
entirely on your own you thought i was
mad
it's incredible but you found your way
you found your way through to a place
of of freedom of compassion and empathy
and also basically that question that
you began the call with
how do i serve i mean that's a question
if if we could all find our way to that
question
genuinely genuinely and stay in
relationship to that question that
that's a
that would prov provide a map david if
we could ask that question in some kind
of very real way
and i'm i'm also very touched by the
fact that you and i are talking to each
other as women
and that there are men on the call that
are just sitting there listening and
taking in what we're saying
and you know there's such a complaint
that somehow
you know males are not available to
the female experience or the
you know and i just want to give you a
shout out in this moment
thank you for listening yeah thank you
to us
yes yeah very cool you're now making me
really scared to interrupt
yeah it was actually a ploy just so we
could keep talking
our ability to make sense of the world
is breaking down
we're making more and more consequential
choices with worse and worse
sense making to inform those choices
which is kind of running increasingly
fast
through the woods increasingly blind
over the last two years rebel wisdom has
interviewed some of the world's top
thinkers now we've brought them together
for an eight-week online course
scents making 101 with daniel
schmacktenberger
diane mucho hamilton john viveki
doshin roshi and more improve your
sense-making
develop your sovereignty and join a
wider community
looking to do the same